Guide to the Josephus Daniels Papers, 1904-1954
Josephus Daniels papers 1904-1954
Daniels, Josephus, 1904-1954
11.6 Linear Feet 22,300 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Josephus Daniels (1904-1954), Secretary of the Navy, Ambassador to Mexico, and editor of the Raleigh News and Observer were acquired through purchase from 1954 to 1981.
Biographical Note
1862, May 18 Born, Washington, N.C.
1880-1893 Edited newspapers in Wilson, Kinston, and Raleigh, N.C.
1885 Attended University of North Carolina summer law school; passed bar examination (never practiced)
1887-1893 State printer for N.C.
1888 Married Adelaide Worth Bagley
1893-1895 Chief of Appointment Division, U.S. Department of the Interior, Washington, D.C.
1894-1913 Editor, Raleigh (N.C.) News and Observer
1896-1916 Member of the Democratic National Committee from N.C.
1898 Publication of The First Fallen Hero. a Biographical Sketch of Worth Bagley. Ensign, U.S.N. (Norfolk, Va., S. W. Bowman.)
1905 Completed purchase of the controlling interest in the News and Observer
1912 Chief, Publicity Bureau, Woodrow Wilson campaign
1913-1921 U.S. Secretary of the Navy
1919 Publication of The Navy and the Nation; War-Time Addresses (New York, G. H. Doran Co.)
1921 - 1933 Editor, News and Observer
1922 Publication of Our Navy at War (Washington, Pictorial Bureau.)
1924 Publication of The Life of Woodrow Wilson. 1856-1924 (Philadelphia, J. C. Winston Co.)
1933-1941 U.S. Ambassador to Mexico
1939 Publication of Tar Heel Editor (Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina Press.), first volume of memoirs
1941 Publication of Editor in Politics (Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina Press.) second volume of memoirs
1942-1948 Editor, News and Observer
1944 Publication of The Wilson Era: Years of Peace. 1910-1917 (Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina Press.)
1946 Publication of The Wilson Era: Years of War and After, 1917-1923 (Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina Press.)
1947 Publication of Shirt-Sleeve Diplomat (Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina Press.), third volume of memoirs
1948, Jan. 15 Died, Raleigh N.C.
Collection Overview
The papers of Josephus Daniels span the period 1904-1954. However, the bulk of the material begins in 1913, while he was Secretary of the Navy in the Wilson administration, and continues until 1942 just after he resigned as Ambassador to Mexico.
The majority of the Daniels papers (approximately 330,000 items) are located in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress. There are, therefore, gaps in Duke's collection. For example, although the Letterbooks, Telegrams, and Pressbooks series cover the period 1913-1921, when Daniels was Secretary of the Navy, there are many months which are not represented in the collection.
The correspondence series covers the period 1917-1951, but primarily dates from 1929 to 1942. It includes personal and business correspondence on a variety of topics. Several letters are from the period when Daniels was U.S. Ambassador to Mexico and relate to claims negotiations between the United States and Mexico. Most of the correspondence from this period, however, relates to Daniels' resignation as ambassador (1942 Jan. 20), with many letters expressing regret at his decision. One such letter (1941 Oct. 31) is from President Roosevelt. There are also a few scattered notes from Eleanor Roosevelt indicating the warm relationship the Daniels family had with the Roosevelts.
Other correspondence concerns the management of the News and Observer and reflects Daniels' political views and civic interests. It also includes correspondence relating to his assistance in securing military commissions, the naming of ships, and other causes. Both the Correspondence and Clippings series contain information about a 1942 editorial in which Daniels condemned the military policy whereby privates were not allowed to date nurses, who were commissioned as second lieutenants. Several people wrote to Daniels applauding this viewpoint.
Also of note are a few letters (1924) from Atlee Pomerene, special counsel for the government, during the period he was investigating major figures in the Teapot Dome oil scandal. There are also many tributes in 1947 paid to Daniels upon his 85th birthday, including a telegram from Harry S Truman, and letters of condolence upon the death of his mother and wife.
Daniels' correspondents, in addition to those mentioned above, include a wide range of public and elected officials including governors, congressmen, cabinet members, and newspaper editors.
The Letterbooks (34 volumes), Telegrams (2 volumes) and Pressbooks (4 volumes) comprise the bulk of the collection (ca. 17,000 items) and cover the period when Daniels was U.S. Secretary of the Navy. Many are official communications stemming from his position, but there are a few personal letters as well. Most of the communiques relate to naval policies, procedures, personnel, and practices. Included are letters relating to Naval Academy appointments, Civil Service jurisdiction, the commissioning and naming of ships, and various naval ceremonial occasions.
Correspondents routinely include President Wilson, his secretary Joseph P. Tumulty, cabinet members, congressmen, and naval officers. Many letters written to the White House and to congressmen concern specific individuals and their requests for naval promotions, commissions, or recommendations for the Naval Academy.
The earliest material in this series concerns events surrounding the American occupation of Veracruz, Mexico in 1914, including lists of the dead and wounded, as well as information regarding ship movements. Speeches and excerpts from Daniels' speeches are also found in some of the press volumes.
Issues reflected in Daniels' correspondence while U.S. Secretary of the Navy include general strengthening of the Navy, particularly on the West Coast; a dispute (1916-1917) regarding the Armor Plate Board and the building of naval vessels at navy yards; naval oil reserves (including a letter of 1917 June 29 to Edward Doheny); Daniels' general concern with the moral welfare of sailors and soldiers as reflected in his efforts to have liquor sales and brothels forbidden in places where men were training for naval service; and a dispute in 1917 with the Navy League regarding the commandant of the Mare Island Navy Yard.
Personal letters relate primarily to Daniels' active involvement in the Democratic Party and the management of the News and Observer. Daniels served as publicity chair for the campaigns of both William Jennings Bryan and Woodrow Wilson. There are numerous letters and telegrams referring to the presidential campaign of 1916 and an analysis by Daniels of why the Democrats lost the 1920 presidential election.
Letters near the end of his tenure as Secretary of the Navy indicate that Daniels would assume more responsibility for the newspaper once he was back in Raleigh. In early 1921, he began to solicit information from naval officers primarily regarding their view of how the Navy functioned in various areas during World War I. He wrote that he was planning to write a series of articles for the National Newspaper Service of Chicago about the Navy's efforts during the war. Among the people to whom Daniels wrote frequently were Secretary of War Newton D. Baker and Senator Benjamin R. Tillman of South Carolina.
The Speeches, Writings, and Related Material, Topical Series, Clippings, Miscellany, and Photograph Series comprise the remainder of the collection.
The "Mexico" subseries in the Topical Series contains information about the relationship between the United States and Mexico on a number of issues, including the petroleum industry, commerce, and a "Memorandum for the Ambassador" outlining steps that may have been taken by the United States government during the early months of 1917 to determine where Mexico would stand in the event the United States entered World War I. Information for this memorandum was taken from Embassy archives and is undated. There are also some papers in this series relating to his tenure on the Board of Trustees Executive Committee at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
The Photograph Series contains: views of Mexico; pictures of Daniels; Lee Slater Overman, Senator from N. C., 1903-1933; Major General Smedley Darlington Butler; Martin H. Glynn, Gov. of New York; and other unidentified persons.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States. Navy
Navy-yards and naval stations -- United States
Shipbuilding -- United States
Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924
Tumulty, Joseph Patrick, 1879-1954
United States. Navy -- Military life
United States. Navy -- Equipment
United States. Navy -- Recruiting, enlistment, etc
United States. Navy -- Appointments and retirements
United States. Navy -- Weapons systems
United States Naval Academy
Daniels, Josephus, 1904-1954
Baker, Newton D. (Newton Diehl), 1871-1937
Tillman, Benjamin Ryan, 1847-1918
Petroleum -- United States -- Reserves
Teapot Dome Scandal, 1921-1924
The News and Observer.
United States -- Foreign relations -- Mexico
Mexico -- Foreign relations -- United States
Veracruz Llave (Mexico)--History -- American occupation, 1914
Contents of Collection
- Information Folder (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1917-1951 bulk 1929-1942
  Business and personal correspondence on a variety of topics and issues including naval policies, appointments and commissions, requests for assistance, speaking engagements, his period as U.S. Ambassador to Mexico, management of the News and Observer, civic and political involvements, and condolences after the deaths of his mother and wife. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1917, Aug. 2-1929, Oct. 3-10, (6 folders)
  - 1929, Oct. 11-1941, Oct. 22, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1941, Oct. 23-Nov. 27, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1941, Nov. 28-Dec. 31, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1942, Jan. 1-Apr. 10, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1942, Apr. 11-1945, May 17, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1945, May 18-1951, June 5 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 7)
- Letterbooks, 1915-1921; Telegrams, 1916-1920; Pressbooks, 1913-1918., 40 Volumes.
  Chiefly official communications maintained while Daniels was U.S. Secretary of the Navy, relating to naval policies, procedures, personnel, and appropriations. The period covered includes the period of unrest in Mexico which resulted in the United States occupation of Veracruz in 1914 and portions of World War I. Persons Daniels corresponded with include President Wilson, members of the White House staff, naval officers, cabinet members, and congressmen. Also includes a few items of personal correspondence. An alphabetical list of correspondents appears in front of each volume with the exception of the pressbooks. Sometimes entries are indexed by the office the person held (such as Attorney General), rather than under the person's name. Pressbooks contain primarily press notices. Arranged chiefly chronologically within each volume.
  - Letterbooks
    - 1915, July 31-Oct. 26, (3 volumes) (Box 8)
    - 1915, Oct. 16-1916, Jan. 7, (3 volumes) (Box 9)
    - 1916, Jan. 6-Mar. 29, (3 volumes) (Box 10)
    - 1916, June 1-Sept. 21, (3 volumes) (Box 11)
    - 1916, Sept. 21-1917, Jan. 19, (3 volumes) (Box 12)
    - 1917, Jan. 19-Mar. 14, (2 volumes) (Box 13)
    - 1917, Mar. 14-May 9, (3 volumes) (Box 14)
    - 1917, May 24-June 29, (2 volumes) (Box 15)
    - 1917, June 29-July 31, (2 volumes) (Box 16)
    - 1917, July 31-Aug. 21, (2 volumes) (Box 17)
    - 1917, Aug. 22-1920, June 4, (3 volumes) (Box 18)
    - 1920, June 4-Sept. 22, (2 volumes) (Box 19)
    - 1920, Sept. 22-1921, Feb. 23, (3 volumes) (Box 20)
  - Telegrams
    - 1916, July 22-1920, Nov. 1, (2 volumes) (Box 21)
  - Pressbooks
    - 1913, Mar. 6-1914, Jan. 6 (Box 22)
    - 1914, Jan. 5-May 22 (Box 23)
    - 1914, May 22-Dec. 19 (Box 24)
    - 1916, Jan. 11-1918, June 6 (Box 25)
- Speeches, Writings, Related Materials, 1919-1946
  Primarily speeches and extracts from speeches delivered while Daniels was Secretary of the Navy. Includes talks given to troops who fought in World War I, numerous naval functions, college commencements, political events, speeches honoring individuals, and numerous other occasions. Also speeches by other individuals, some of them honoring Daniels and fragments of speeches by unidentified persons. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1919, Mar.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1920-1946, (7 folders) (Box 27)
  - Undated and Miscellany, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Various speakers, 1919-1944 and Undated
  - Unidentified Speakers, 1933-1946 and undated
- Topical Series,1914-1945 and undated.
  This series is divided into three subseries, the Navy, Mexico, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Papers are arranged chronologically within each topic.
  - Navy, 1914-1945 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    Chiefly relates to the leasing of naval oil lands, including printed information about the investigation by Senator Thomas J. Walsh, that led to the uncovering of the Teapot Dome oil scandal. Also plans of the day on board the U.S.S. Rushmore for Nov. 1944-June 1945. It is unclear how these plans relate to Daniels, but may be records of one of his sons who served in the Marine Corps during World War II.
  - Mexico, 1935-1941 and undated
    Consists of memorandums regarding relations between Mexico and the United States on a number of issues, a list of American ambassadors to Mexico from 1899 to Daniels' tenure, and other miscellany items.
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1940-1946 Apr.
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1946, May-1954 and undated (Box 29)
    Includes Board of Trustee Executive Committee minutes, correspondence, reports, printed material, and other papers related to the university during Daniels' membership on the Board of Trustees.
- Clippings, (2 folders)
  Includes reviews of his works The Wilson Era: Years of Peace, 1910-1917, (1944) and The Wilson Era: Years of War and After. 1917-1923, (1946) and articles about various speeches he made. Others date from the period when Daniels was Secretary of the Navy and Ambassador to Mexico (a few from Spanish newspapers). Also some written upon Daniels' return to Raleigh to edit the News and Observer and the occasion of his 85th birthday.
  - Clippings (Box 29)
- Miscellany, 1904-1947 and undated, (2 folders)
  Papers relating to North Carolina Home-Coming Week (Oct. 14-19, 1929 ) of which Daniels was Vice-Chair, book reviews of The Wilson Era: Years of Peace, 1910-1917 and The Wilson Era: Years of War and After, 1917-1923, a report on the Battle of Munroe Farm, now called Battlefield Farm, near Fort Bragg, N.C., and other miscellaneous papers. Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellany (Box 29)
- Photographs, 1933 and undated, (2 folders)
  Includes views of Mexico, photographs of Daniels, and other political and military figures, and several unidentified persons.
  - Photographs (Box 29)